Guide to the Chester and Phebe Fuson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Chester and Phebe Fuson Papers
1905-1965
RG 143
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
Letters, writings, collected material, and photos document religious work and political conditions in South China from 1905 to 1929. Chester Garfield and Phebe Meeker Fuson were American Presbyterian missionaries in South China from 1905 to 1929. Chester Fuson taught at Canton Christian College (later Lingnan University) from 1905 to 1917. Thereafter he was an administrator and educator for the South China Mission of the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)
Fuson, Chester Garfield, 1881-1965
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Fuson.
Biographical / Historical
1881 Born in Wakeeney, Kansas
1905 B.A., College of Emporia
1905-1917 Taught at Canton Christian College (later known as Lingnan University)
1908-1909 Accompanied American scientist on magnetic survey, traveling 5,500 miles from Peiping through Honan, Shensi, Kansu, Sinkiang, over the Kwenlun and Himalaya mountains to India. Elected a Fellow of the Royal Geographical Society for participation in this survey.
1909 Married Phebe Meeker. Children: Ben, Nelson, William.
1917 Appointed by Board of Foreign Missions of Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. to serve its South China Mission. While in Canton, CGF was Executive Secretary of the Board of Primary Education of the provincial Christian Education Association and was on the faculty of Pui Ying Middle School as Director of Teacher Training.
1924 Ordained by Topeka Presbytery
1930 Litt. D., College of Emporia
1938 Transferred to Linhsien (Linchow) where CGF aided in educational work, was in charge of country churches and was acting superintendent of the Linhsien Hospital from 1941 on. He was South China Mission Executive Secretary until furlough in 1944.
1946 Returned to Linhsien following furlough; was active in relief and rehabilitation work.
1949 Retired
1965 Died in Duarte, California
Scope and Contents
The Fuson Papers provide valuable documentation of religious and political conditions in South China from 1905 to 1949. The family correspondence in Series I includes more than 200 letters from Chester and Phebe Fuson to their sons and other family members; it is most substantive for the years 1938 to 1940. General correspondence includes printed and typescript report letters, early letters to the Trustees of Canton Christian College (1906-1908) that are particularly interesting for their descriptions of College athletic activities, correspondence with members of the First Presbyterian Church of Pueblo, Colorado, which supported CGF as its foreign pastor, and miscellaneous other correspondence to or from the Fusons. Writings by the Fusons, collected material and memorabilia provide additional documentation of their life and work in South China.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1906-1950
II. Writings, 1905-1940, n.d.
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1915-1965, n.d.
IV. Collected Material, 1924-1949, n.d.
V. Addendum, 1907-1959, n.d.
Missions -- China; Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- China; Fuson, Chester Garfield, 1881-1965; Fuson, Phebe; Canton Christian College
- Correspondence, 1906-1950; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Letters, 1918, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2-10)
  - General correspondence
    - Letters, 1906-1948, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-18)
- Writings, 1905-1940, n.d; Series II
  - Of Chester Fuson
    - Account of first trip into Canton city, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Account of village clan fights near CCC campus, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "First Book in Geography", c.1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Narrative of 2nd South China track meet held in Canton including CCC and many other schools, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Narrative of expedition from Canton to Linhsien, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Untitled, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration Pui Ying Middle School", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Linhsien Station Report", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Interesting Developments Due to War Conditions", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "When Christ Came to China", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "An Incident in the Jap-Chinese War", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Orphan of Chau", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Lovest Thou Me", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Of Phebe Meeker Fuson
    - "Calls in Canton", 1924 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "If You Were Bombed-?", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Personal Report of Mrs. Chester G. Fuson", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "In a Sedan Chair", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Anonymous
    - "The First Protestant Martyr in China", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Light Out of Darkness" (a skit), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1915-1965, n.d.; Series III
  - Autobiography of CGF (183 p.), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Autobiographical sketch, n.d (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Farewell messages to Fusons on their retirement, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous personal memoranda (incl. financial statement and instructions regarding burial), 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Memorial Minute regarding CGF, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous printed items that document the work of the Fusons, 1915-1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Collected Material, 1924-1949, n.d.; Series IV
  - Photograph of Linhsien Presbytery, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Canton Station report, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - South China Mission report, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Linchow Station report, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ming Sum School for the Blind, Canton - report, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Circular letters, bulletins, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Unidentified Chinese language material, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Addendum, 1907-1959, n.d.; Series V
  - Letters to family from Fusons, incl. written from Manila, Hong Kong, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Letters to family from Fusons, written from Linchow and Linhsien, 1939-1949, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Letters to Fusons: from Chinese friend, farewell letters from church and hospital, and from a leper, 1943, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Fusons to churches in U.S. and "Dear Friends"; circular letters of other missionaries, incl. from Florence Meeker Raetz, who was in charge of Door of Hope Mission, Canton, 1927-1951 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Writings by Chester Fuson: "A Trip to Loh Fau Mountain"; "A Modern Chinese Wedding"; "Three Weeks in Kwangtung and Kwangsi", 1907, ca. 1920s, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Writings by Fusons: "The Taai Cheung Ling Paai (Aborigine settlement)"; Station report; "A Trip to Macao", ca. 1938-1948, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Autobiographical writings by Chinese students, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Literary Grandmothers" by E. Marshall; "Principal's Report" by Wan Kam Ming (Pui Ying Middle School in Hong Kong), 1959, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Photocopied selections from autograph book of Phebe Fuson, with explanatory notes by son William M. Fuson; program from memorial meeting for Mrs. Van Etten, Linchow, ca. 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Photographs (loose) - incl. Canton Christian College staff, Presbyterian mission staff, Bible study group, Canton Christian College soccer team, Sunday School group photo, students, Christmas play, illustrations of Robert Morrison, 1905-1933, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Photographs (matted) - incl. first year high school class at Canton Christian College, faculty of Pui Ying School, Chinese teachers' wives, modern Chinese wedding, 1905-1920, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Photograph of mission staff and children on occasion of Machle retirement, with sheet providing identification of all, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Oversize panoramic photo of students and staff of Union Normal School, Canton, 1930s (Box OVd1)